Personal Papers of Elmer Ellsworth Brown: 1827-1936 MC 16
New York University Archives
Elmer Ellsworth Brown Papers
1827-1936
MC 16
New York University Archives
11.5 linear feet 11.5 linear feet (28 boxes)
Arrangement
Files are arranged either alphabetically or chronologically within each series.
This collection is divided into ten series.
Scope and Contents
This collection of the personal papers of Elmer Ellsworth Brown is divided into ten series. See container list for specifics.
Biographical Note
Elmer Ellsworth Brown (1861-1934), educator and university administrator, was born in Kiantone, Chautaugua County, New York on August 26, 1861, the fourth and youngest child of Russell McCrary and Electa Louisa (Sherman) Brown. His father's ancestors had moved from Connecticut to Albany County, New York in the early eighteenth-century, and then settled in western New York around 1800. In 1862, the family moved west to Sublette, Illinois, but returned shortly thereafter to Kiantone, when Elmer's father enlisted in the Union Army. In 1864, the family returned to Sublette following the discharge of Russell Brown on account of poor health.
The Brown family lived in virtual poverty. Their farmland on the Illinois prairie produced enough for family consumption; additional income was received through a small soldier's pension and money earned by the children in performing neighborhood chores Russell Brown, the grandson of a Congregational minister, completed his formal schooling in New York State and yearned for a college education, but financial conditions forced him to turn toward farming. He compensated for his lack of formal collegiate instruction by immersing himself in literature and poetry, an interest in which he imparted to his children. His suppressed desire for higher learning was to be manifested and fulfilled in all four of his children, each of whom were to acquire a college education and enter into professional careers.
Elmer Brown did not begin formal schooling until he was eight years old. A precocious and energetic child, he proved to be a serious student. In 1874, while attending Sublette High School, Brown competed with students for teacher certification and finished first in the county examinations. His youth however, precluded his appointment as a teacher. Two years later, he entered the State Normal University and soon began the alternation of teaching and study in Illinois.
In 1878, Brown became principal of the public schools in Rockport, and -in 1880 served as a teacher in the public schools in Astoria. In 1881, he graduated from Illinois State Normal University and became principal of public schools in Belvidere, serving until 1884 when family financial circumstances forced him away from education. His older brother, Isaac Eddy Brown, held the position of State Secretary of the Illinois Y.M.C.A.. and Elmer became Assistant Secretary, a position in which he occupied until 1887, when he had earned enough money to continue his college education.
In the fall of 1887, Brown entered the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor to study the theory and practice of education under Professor William H. Payne, and the history and philosophy of education under Professor Burke A. Hinsdale. His Normal School preparation had provided him with advanced standing so that he was able to complete the four-year course in two years, graduating in June 1889, with Phi Beta Kappa honors. Two days following commencement, Brown was married to his cousin Fanny F. Eddy of Detroit, the daughter of the Reverend Zachery Eddy, a prominent Michigan clergyman.
Elmer and Fanny Brown traveled to Europe in 1889 and settled in Germany, where Elmer enrolled in the University of Halle-Wittenberg to study the philosophy of education. At the end of the academic year, he was awarded the Ph.D. degree, completing and publishing his German-language thesis, "The Position of States Toward the Church and Carrying Out Religious Education in the Schools in Prussia, England, and the United States," (1890). Returning to the United States, Brown became a high school principal in Jackson, Michigan, a position at which he served until 1891, when he was selected as acting Assistant Professor of the Art and Science of Teaching in the University of Michigan, temporarily replacing his mentor, B. A. Hinsdale. Before his first year was completed, he received an invitation to join the faculty at the University of California at Berkeley.
Brown spent the next fourteen years at Berkeley. He was appointed to the newly-created chair of the Science and Art of Teaching in 1892, and soon formulated plans for the organization and development of the University's Department of Pedagogy. During his tenure at the University of California, he wrote his best known scholarly works, The Origins of American State Universities (1903), and The Making of Our Middle Schools (1903), a historical study of secondary education in the United States. Through his publications and his work in developing the Pedagogy department at Berkeley, Brown became a national figure in education. In 1905, he was elected to serve a two-year term as president of the National Council on Education.
In 1906, Elmer Brown was appointed United States Commissioner of Education by President Theodore Roosevelt. Building upon the work of his predecessor, William Torrey Harris, he succeeded in enlarging the Bureau of Education by establishing special divisions in higher education and school administration, as well as by extending the services of the Bureau throughout the country. As national spokesman for education, Brown traveled extensively addressing the myriad problems and issues in elementary secondary, and higher education. A selection of his many speeches and essays were published in Government By Influence and Other Addresses (1910). He was reappointed to the position by William Howard Taft in 1908, and served until 1911, when he was chosen to be Chancellor of New York University. He held that office until 1933, and the title of Chancellor Emeritus until his death in New York City on November 3, 1934.
Sources:
Frusciano, Thomas J. "Elmer Ellsworth Brown: Mohonker, Scholar, and Educator, 1861-1934," unpublished address delivered at the Hudson Valley & Mohonk Heritage Program, Lake Mohonk, New York, July 10, 1984. New York University Archives.
Jones, Theodore Francis, ed. New York University, 1832-1932. New York: New York University Press, 1933.
Voorhis, Harold O. A Tribute to Elmer Ellsworth Brown, 1861-1934. New York: Hall of American Artists, New York University, 1944.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open to researchers. It is in
off-site storage
Provenance
These papers, through an administrative transfer, were accessioned to the University Archives from the Office of the Vice President and Secretary in 1976.
Alameda County (CA) Teachers' Institute.; American Academy of Arts and Letters.; Angell, James Burill, 1829-1916; Armory Show (1913: New York, N.Y.).; Bailey, Thomas P.; Brown, Electra Louisa; Brown, Fanny Eddy; Brown, Isaac Eddy; Brown, Russell McCary; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947; Churchill, Winston, 1871-1947; Cuerly, Ellwood P.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952; Draper, A. S., (Andrew Sloan), 1848-1913; Eddy Family Association; Eddy, Zachery; Finley, John; Gilman, Daniel Colt, 1931-1909; Grandi, Dino, 1895-; Harris, William Torrey, 1835-1909; Howison, George Holmes, 1834-1917; James, Edmund J., (Edmund Janes), 1855-1925; Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1852-1937; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Kellogg, Martin; Keppel, Frederick, 1845-1912; Lake Mohonk Conference of Friends of the Indian.; Lake Mohonk Conference on International Arbitration.; Louisiana Purchase Exposition Co. (Saint Louis, Mo.).; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918; Muensterberg, Hugo; New York University.; Pan-American Exposition (1901: Buffalo, NY).; Pardee, George; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937; Sanford, Emerson C.; Scripture, E.W., (Edward Wheeler), 1864-; Slate, Frederick; Smiley, Daniel; Taft, William H., (William Howard), 1857-1930; Thorndike, Edward L., (Edward Lee), 1874-1949; United States Department of the Interior. Bureau of Education.; University of California, Berkeley. School of Education.; University of Halle-Wittenberg (Germany).; University of Michigan.; University of the State of New York.; Voorhis, Harold O.; Wheeler, Benjamin Ide, 1854-1927; Young Men's Christian Association (Illinois).; account books.; Address books.; Arbitration and award, International.; Belvidere (Ill.); Berkeley (Calif.); Biographies.; Broadsides.; Curricula.; Diaries.; Education |x Philosophy.; Education |x Study and Teaching |z United States.; genealogies.; Indians, treatment of |z North America; Jackson |z Michigan (State).; Ledgers (account books).; Letterpress copybooks.; Manuscripts for publication.; Mohonk, Lake (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.); Oakland (Calif.).; Obituaries.; San Francisco (Calif.) |x Earthquake and fire, 1906.; Sublette (Ill.); Wills.
- Series I. BIOGRAPHICAL AND GENEALOGICAL 1880-1934 (Box 1, Folders 1-9)
  Scope and Contents note
  The initial files of the Brown personal papers contain biographical and genealogical material on the families of Elmer Ellsworth Brown and Fanny Eddy Brown. Numerous biographical sketches of Elmer Brown, the Brown family tree, biographical sketch of Isaac Eddy Brown, notes on the Brown family compiled by Elmer Brown, and material relating to the Eddy Family Association are also included in these files.
  - Biographical Sketches (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Immediate Relatives of Elmer E. Brown and Fanny E. Brown, 1902, 1927, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Isaac Eddy: Family Tree and Biographical Sketch, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brown Family: Notes compiled by Elmer E. Brown, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cowles, Dwight L. and Mary Brown, [1924] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Eddy, Nathan, and Samuel Cochran: Revolutionary War Record, 1902, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Eddy Family Association, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Marriage Certificate (informal): Elmer E. Brown and Fanny F. Eddy, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1880, 1904-1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II. CORRESPONDENCE AND RELATED PAPERS AMONG RELATIVES 1827-1935 (Boxes 1-5)
  This series contains extensive correspondence exchanged between Elmer Brown and his wife Fanny, 1886-1929, including letters from Elmer Brown when he was in Berkeley during the San Francisco earthquake on April 18, 1906; correspondence and miscellaneous papers of members of the Eddy family and Brown family; collections of verse written by Elmer Brown, Fanny Brown, other relatives and friends; and wills, obituaries, and tributes concerning Fanny Brown.
  - Elmer E. Brown to Fanny Eddy, 1886 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Elmer E. Brown to Fanny E. Brown, 1896 July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - EEB to FEB, 1898 June.-1898 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - EEB to FEB, 1901 June. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - EEB to FEB, July (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - EEB to FEB: San Francisco Earthquake, Apr. 18, 1906, 1906 Apr.-1906 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - EEB to FEB (from Washington DC), 1906 June.-1906 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - EEB to FEB, 1907 June.-1907 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - EEB to FEB, 1908 May-1908 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - EEB to FEB, 1909 June.-1909 July (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - EEB to FEB, 1911 Mar. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - EEB to FEB, 1919 Sept.-1919 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - EEB to FEB, 1925 Oct.-1925 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - EEB to FEB, 1926 Jan.-1926 Mar. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - EEB to FEB, 1929 May-1929 July (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - EEB to FEB (from Lake Mohonk), 1929 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - EEB to FEB (from Coney Island), 1929 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - EEB to FEB (enroute to/from Cuba), 1929 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - EEB to FEB (enroute to/from Costa Rica and Cuba), 1929 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - EEB to FEB (telegram), 1931 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - EEB to FEB, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fanny Eddy to Elmer E. Brown, 1889 June. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fanny E. Brown to EEB, 1904 June. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - FEB to EEB, 1908 Aug. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - FEB to EEB, 1910 May-1910 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - FEB to EEB, 1911 Feb. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - FEB to EEB, 1919 Apr.-1919 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - FEB to EEB, 1924 Feb.-1924 Apr. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - FEB to EEB, 1925 Oct.-1925 Dec. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - FEB to EEB, Jan.-Mar.. 1926 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - FEB to EEB, 1927 Dec. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - FEB to EEB, 1929 May (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - FEB to EEB, 1928 June. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - FEB to EEB, 1929 Sept. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - FEB to EEB, 1929 Oct.-1929 Dec. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - FEB to EEB, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - FEB to EEB: Verse, 1891-1932 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - FEB to EEB: Verse, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - FEB: Manuscripts of Verse, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - FEB: Collection of Modern Verse in University Library, 1923-1933 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - FEB: Wills, Obituaries, and Tributes, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Browning, Dorothy (niece) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Relatives of Fanny Brown
  - Cochran, David H. (uncle), 1903-1904 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Curtiss, Alice Eddy (sister) and Edward (brother-in-law), undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Eddy, Frank W. (brother) and Florence (sister-in-law), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Eddy, Zachary (father): Sermons, Notes, Correspondence, 1827 1828 1863 1887-1897 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lyons, Albert E. (nephew; son of Edith and Albert Lyons), [1931]-1935 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lyons, Edith (sister) and Albert (brother-in-law) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lyons, Lucia E. (niece; daughter of Edith and Albert Lyons), undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Lucking, Frances Eddy (niece), undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mundy, Kathleen (niece; daughter of Frank W. Eddy), undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Munger, Florence (niece) (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Standish, Mrs. Colburn (niece; daughter of Frank W. Eddy), 1927 1930 1933 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Treat, Alice (niece), 1901 1922-1935 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Treat, Ethel (niece), 1902 1933 1935 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Treat, Leonard A. (brother-in-law): The New England Primer, (1887) 1889 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Treat, Rev. Roger Eddy (nephew), 1932-1935 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Relatives of Elmer E. Brown
  - Brown, Alice (niece), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Electa Louisa Sherman (mother), 1889 1899 1900 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Isaac Eddy (brother), 1891-1927 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Brown, Russell McCrary (father), 1887 1888 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fairchild, Lillian (sister), 1889, 1900, 1904, 1907, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - McMurry, Fred R. (nephew; son of Lida B. McMurry), 1922-1935 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - McMurry, Karl F. (nephew; son of Lida B. McMurry), 1911-1935 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - McMurry, Lida B. (sister), 1889-1933 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - McMurry, Lida B. (sister), 1934 Jan.-1934 Oct. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - McMurry, Lida B. (sister), 1934 Nov. -1935 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Ponafidine, Madame Emma (distant cousin? and author), 1922-1935 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Folder not found (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Family Correspondence re: Position of Chancellor at New York University: Isaac Eddy Brown, Frank W. Eddy, and Leonard A. Treat, 1911 Mar.-1911 Apr. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Family Correspondence, Miscellaneous and Unidentified: Corydon Brown, Fred Cowles, Frances Marvin Eddy, Samuel A. Eddy, Florence Knapp, Frank M. McMurry, Janet Munger, Mary[?], Lorraine[?], and Peggy [?], 1900-1934 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series III. VERSE 1903-1933 (Box 5, folders 15-20)
  This series contains contains writings of friends and relatives of Elmer Brown in manuscript form.
  - Arnold, J. Loring (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Lyons, Edith Eddy, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Maclean, Eda, 1928 Feb. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Walker, F. A, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Authors: James Buckham, Grace Keat Hill, Robert Underwood Johnson, Edwin Markham, Lawrence McLouth, Stephen Phillips, Leon J. Richardson, Jones B. Smith [EEB?], and other anonymous authors (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Relatives: Alice M. Eddy, Fanny E. Brown, Elmer E. Brown, Edith E. Lyons, Alice E. Treat, Kathleen Mundy, F. C. Hudson (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Series IV. ADDRESS BOOKS, DIARIES JOURNALS AND LEDGERS 1875-1934 (Boxes 6-15)
  Elmer Brown maintained a diary for each year from 1875-1934, with many years containing incomplete entries. Along with this valuable personal record are numerous account books, journals, ledgers, all of which document his financial affairs, and address books of people he associated or corresponded with throughout his professional life.
  - 1875 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1876 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1877 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 1878 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1879 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1880 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 1881 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 1882 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 1883 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1884 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1885 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 1886 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 1887 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 1888 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1889 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1890 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1891 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 1892 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 1893 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1894 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1895 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1896 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1897 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 1898 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1899 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1900 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1901 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1902 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - 1903 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1904 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1905 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1906 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1907 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1908 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 1909 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - 1910 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 1911 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - 1912 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - 1913 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 1914 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 1917 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 1918 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 1919 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 1920 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 1921 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 1922 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1923 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 1924 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 1925 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1926 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 1927 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 1928 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 1929 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 1930 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 1931 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 1932 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - 1933 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - 1934 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1912 Jan.-1912 Nov. (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Series V. PUBLIC LIFE, CULTURAL ACTIVITIES, AND TRAVEL 1901-1903 (Boxes 16-18)
  This series includes subject files, arranged alphabetically, pertaining to personal and professional activities pursued by Brown outside the area of education. These files include material on his travel to Europe in 1923; the Lake Mohonk conferences on Indian and Other Dependent People, and International Arbitration; invitations and programs to numerous social and cultural activities in New York City; and a large collection of musical, opera, and theater programs.
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1914 1916 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - American Institute, 1914 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Armory Show, 1913 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Ethnic Groups, Meetings re:, 1911, 1922, 1925 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - 1923 July-1923 Aug. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Europe, Trip to, 1923 Sept.-1923 Nov. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Europe, Trip to, 1932 Mar. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Events in which EEB participated, 1911-1930 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Grandi, Dino (Italian Minister of Foreign Affairs): Welcome Ceremony, Nov. 21, 1931) (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Health and Medicine, including International Congresses, 1912-1932 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Institute of Politics, 1921-1933 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Invitations (formal) and Acknowledgments from Distinguished People (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Mohonk, Lake: Conference on the Indian and Other Dependent Peoples, 1917 Sept.-1917 Oct. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Mohonk, Lake: Conference on International Arbitration, 1912-1917 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Mohonk, Lake: Mountain House (Mr.and Mrs. Daniel Smiley), 1911-1932 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Musical Events, Programs of (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - New York City Official Occasions (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - New York City Commercial Tercentenary Commission, 1914 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Pan American Exposition, Buffalo, New York 1901: Printed Material (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Peace Congresses and Related Affairs (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Programs (miscellaneous) (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Religious Services and Lectures: Programs and Notices (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Theater Programs, 1912-1920 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Theater Programs (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Series VI. PERSONAL AND PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS 1869-1911 (Boxes 19-23)
  Brown's student and professional activities in education are documented extensively in these files of correspondence and related papers. This includes his initial schooling in Sublette, Illinois, his years at the Illinois State Normal University, service as principal of public schools in Belvidere, Illinois, his tenure as Assistant State Secretary of the Illinois Y.M.C.A., his student years at the University of Michigan, 1887-1889, and at the University of Halle-Wittenberg in Germany, 1889-1890, high school principal in Jackson, Michigan, 1890-1891, and acting Assistant professor of the Science and Art of Teaching, 1891-1892.
  A large number of correspondence files concern the development of the Department of Pedagogy at the University of California at Berkeley, 1892-1906. These files include extensive correspondence with Brown's colleagues at Berkeley such as presidents Martin Kellogg and Benjamin I. Wheeler, and professors Frederick Slate, George Howison, and numerous educators across the United States, including James B. Angell, Nicholas Murray Butler, William Torrey Harris, Thomas P. Bailey, Jr., E. C. Sanford, Edmund J. James, Andrew S. Draper, Ellwood P. Cubberly, Hugo Muensterberg, John H. Finley, Winston Churchill, Henry M. MacCracken, Daniel Colt Gilman, E. W. Scripture, and Governor George Pardee of California. Of particular interest are letters from John Dewey when the educator was serving as a professor of philosophy at the University of Michigan and the University of Chicago. Also included in the professional correspondence files are departmental reports on student enrollment, Brown's course notebooks for "Theory of Education" and "School Systems," and printed material relating to both the Department of Pedagogy and general university concerns. Material concerning Brown's activities as U.S. Commissioner of Education, 1906-1911, include correspondence files and letter books of outgoing correspondence. The final folder relates to Brown's decision to accept the invitation to become Chancellor of New York University in 1911.
  - Correspondence and Papers, 1869-1881 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Illinois State Normal University: Miscellaneous Notes; Fine Arts and Literature Notes, 1878-1888 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Belvidere, Illinois (Principal of Public Schools), 1881-1884 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Belvidere, Illinois: School Reports, 1881-1884 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Illinois State Y.M.C.A. (Assistant State Secretary), 1885-1887 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Michigan, University of (student), 1887-1889 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Halle-Wittenberg, University of (graduate student), 1889-1890 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Jackson, Michigan (high school principal), 1890-1891 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Michigan, University of (acting Assistant Professor of Science and Art of Teaching), 1891-1892 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1892 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1893 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1894 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1895 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - California, University of (Berkeley): Correspondence, 1896 (Box 20, Folder 5)